Guide to the Darlington Family Papers, 1753-1921 DAR.1925.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Darlington Family Papers
1753-1921
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Darlington family
DAR.1925.01
18 Linear Feet (28 boxes, 61 volumes)
The Darlington family lived in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, from the late eighteenth through the early nineteenth centuries. William M. Darlington and his wife, Mary Carson O'Hara Darlington, collected thousands of books and manuscripts documenting the frontier history of western Pennsylvania. The collection includes financial, personal and legal papers, and documentation of collecting activities and ephemera related to William M. Darlington and his family. Formats of materials include ledger books, research notes, manuscripts, personal diaries, photographic prints and negatives, letters, and artwork. Digital reproductions of this collection are available online.
Biography
The Darlingtons of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania trace their roots in America to Abraham Darlington of Cheshire County, England, who joined his aunt and uncle in Chester County, Pennsylvania, at the turn of the eighteenth century. Abraham's great-grandson, Benjamin Darlington (1790-1856), left Chester County and settled in Pittsburgh with his wife, Agnes McCullough. The Darlingtons of Pittsburgh are related to the Schenley and O'Hara families through the marriage of Benjamin and Agnes's son, William McCullough Darlington (1815-1889), to Mary Carson O'Hara.
William M. Darlington was a successful lawyer and one of the foremost experts in the colonial history of western Pennsylvania and the Ohio Valley. Mary shared her husband's passion for history, and was very proud of her family's ancestry, which she traced back to Irish nobility through her grandfather, James O'Hara. Through her father, Mary inherited Guyasuta: James O'Hara's estate near present-day Sharpsburg, Pennsylvania.
William and Mary raised three children at Guyasuta, O'Hara, Mary, and Edith. A fourth child, Hillborn, died in childhood. For more detailed biographies of each family member, see the scope and content note provided for each individual's papers. William was the primary collector of his family's extensive library of books and manuscripts. After William's death in 1889, his widow and children maintained and added to his collection. In 1918 and 1925, William's daughters Edith and Mary donated the family library and manuscript collection to the University of Pittsburgh. These materials include original letters by George Washington, Colonel Henry Bouquet, General Anthony Wayne, Hugh Henry Brackenridge, General Cornwallis, General James Wilkinson, Alexander Hamilton, Andrew Jackson and Daniel Webster. William M. Darlington also obtained and preserved John James Audubon's complete set of Birds of America.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains the nineteenth and early twentieth century personal, legal and financial papers of William M. Darlington and his family, including: his wife, Mary Carson O'Hara Darlington; his children, O'Hara Darlington, Mary Carson Darlington and Edith Dennison Darlington Ammon; his father, Benjamin Darlington; and his wife's grandparents, James and Mary Carson O'Hara. Documents include personal letters, business correspondence, financial and travel documents, art on paper, photographs, scrapbooks of news clippings and personal ephemera. The collection highlights William's book collecting, including correspondence with book dealers and individuals interested in his library, book catalogs and orders, receipts for purchases, notes and essays written by William, and topical inventories of the family library when it resided at Guyasuta.
Arrangement
Series I. James O'Hara Papers, 1777-1880
Series II. Benjamin Darlington Papers, 1815-1852
Series III. William M. Darlington Papers, 1837-1889
Series IV. Mary Carson O'Hara Darlington Papers, 1753-1908
Series V. O'Hara Darlington Papers, 1874-1916
Series VI. Mary Carson Darlington Papers, 1833-1913
Series VII. Edith Dennison Darlington Ammon Papers, 1881-1882, 1908-1919
Series VIII. Family Papers, 1826-1914
Series IX. Bound News Clipping Books, 1898-1917
Series X. Scrapbooks, ca. 1850-1915
Series XI. Photographs, 1885-1888
Series XII. Mary Carson Darlington Artwork, 1867-1925
Series XIII. Oversize Materials, 1785-1899
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Part of the original donation of William M. Darlington's family library to the University of Pittsburgh in 1918 and 1925 by his daughters, Edith Darlington Ammon and Mary Carson Darlington.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of this collection are available online. Digitized images of the Darlington Family photographs are available at http://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/darlington-family-papers.
Custodial History
The Darlington Family Papers consist of three separate accessions. The first group of materials was donated to the University of Pittsburgh by Mary Carson Darlington and Edith Darlington Ammon in 1918. In 1925, Mary Carson Darlington bequeathed the remainder of the family library and a number of ephemeral items to the University. The third accession consisted of a collection of correspondence between Edith Darlington and Mittie Hemphill that was presented to the University of Pittsburgh in November of 1977 by Richard Johnson of the New England Historic Genealogical Society. The Darlington-Hemphill letters had been gifted to the New England Historic Genealogical Society earlier in 1977 by Mrs. Henry Mayo, a granddaughter of Mittie Hemphill.
This collection was located in the Darlington Memorial Library in the University's Cathedral of Learning until 2007 when it was moved to the ULS Archives Service Center for processing, storage, preservation and service. However, it remains in the custodianship of the ULS Special Collections Department.
Previous Citation
Darlington Family Papers, 1753-1921, DAR.1925.01, Darlington Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Separated Material
Large artwork, framed photographs, bound volumes and the majority of photographs are stored separately from manuscript materials. Throughout the finding aid, separated materials are indicated as "oversize" if they are stored separately due to size, and "volume" if they are bound items.
Bibliography
Davison, Elizabeth M. and Ellen B. McKee, eds. Annals of Old Wilkinsburg and Vicinity: The Village, 1788-1888, Wilkinsburg, Pa: Group for Historical Research, 1940.
Bomberger, C. M. Brush Creek Tales. Jeannette, Pa: Jeannette Publishing, 1950.
Boucher, John Newton. A Century and a Half of Pittsburg and Her People New York: The Lewis Publishing Company, 1908.
Chalfant, Ella. A Goodly Heritage: Earliest Wills on an American Frontier. Pittsburgh, Pa: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1955.
Cope, Gilbert. The Genealogy of the Darlington Family. West Chester,Pa: Printed by the committee for the family, 1900.
Course of Study in Geographic, Biographic and Historic Pittsburgh. Pittsburgh, Pa: The Board of Public Education, 1921.
Fleming, George. History of Pittsburgh and Environs, from Prehistoric Days to the Beginning of the American Revolution New York: The American Historical Society, Inc., 1922.
Pittsburgh Freemasons, Lodge no. 45. History of Lodge no. 45, 1785-1910. Pittsburgh, Pa.,: Press of Republic Bank Note Company, 1912.
Harper, Frank C. Pittsburgh of Today, Its Resources and People. New York: The American Historical Society, Inc., 1931-1932.
Herbert, Anne Hemphill. Personal Memories of the Darlington Family at Guyasuta. Pittsburgh, Pa: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1949.
Kussart, Sarepta Cooper. The Allegheny River. Pittsburgh, Pa: Burgum Printing Company, 1938.
Starrett, Agnes Lynch. Through One Hundred and Fifty Years: The University of Pittsburgh. Pittsburgh, Pa: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1937.
Wilson, Erasmus, and Weston Arthur Goodspeed Standard History of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania.. Chicago: H.R. Cornell & Co., 1898.
Shine, Bernice. "Oakland: Mary Croghan Schenley: Schenley Park Donated by a Girl Whose Romance Shocked a Queen." Pittsburgh Sun-Telegraph, 15 September 1941.
Schock, Hiram. The History of the Masonic Fund Society for the County of Allegheny. Pittsburgh, Pa: 1923.
Rubin, Julius. Canal or Railroad? Imitation and Innovation in the Response to the Erie Canal in Philadelphia, Baltimore, and Boston. Philadelphia: American Philosophical Society, 1961.
Patch, Margery Hulburt. "The Darlington Family Collection." The Pittsburgh Record v1.
Military personnel; Public officers; Entrepreneurs; Lawyers; Watercolors (Paintings); Souvenirs; Sketches; Receipts (Financial records); Photographs; Obituaries; Clippings (Information artifacts); Maps; Manuscripts (Documents); Correspondence; Ledgers (Account books); Business and Industry; Land surveys; Personal papers; Europe -- Description and travel; Women; Egypt -- Description and travel; Allegheny County (Pa.) -- History; Wills -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh.; Watercolor painting, American -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Shipping -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Photography -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Prints, American -- 19th century -- Collectors and collecting; Glass manufacture -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Indians of North America -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Frontier and pioneer life -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Collectors and collecting -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Book collecting -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Fort Pitt (Pa.) -- History; Ireland -- History; O'Hara (Pa.: Township) -- History; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- History; Pittsburgh Region (Pa.) -- History; Sharpsburg (Pa.) -- History; United States -- History -- French and Indian War, 1755-1763; Color prints (Prints); Diaries; Diplomas; Envelopes; Essays; Ammon, Edith Dennison Darlington; O'Hara family; Darlington family; O'Hara, James, 1752-1819; McCullough, Jane; Hemphill, Mittie; Darlington, Mary Carson; Darlington, O'Hara; Darlington, Mary C. (Mary Carson); Darlington, William M. (William McCullough); Darlington, Benjamin; Brackenridge, H. M. (Henry Marie); Bouquet, Henry; O'Hara, Mary Carson; Allegheny Engine and Hose Company; Allegheny Valley Railroad Company; Daughters of the American Revolution; Historical Society of Pennsylvania; Pittsburgh Amateur Photographers' Society; Pittsburgh Gas Works; Pittsburgh Glass Works; Sharpsburg Bridge Company; Bank of the United States (1816-1836). Pittsburgh Branch; Washington & Jefferson College (Washington, Pa.); Pennsylvania Railroad
- James O'Hara Papers, 1777-1880; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  James O'Hara (1753-1819) left his home in County Mayo, Ireland, in 1773 to settle in Philadelphia. In 1774, he was appointed a government Indian agent, and traveled to western Pennsylvania where he traded with Indians at Fort Pitt on behalf of an eastern company, and purchased extensive lands from the federal government. In 1788, James became the second president of the Bank of Pennsylvania, and two years later he wed Mary Carson (1760-1834) of Philadelphia, and brought her to Pittsburgh. George Washington appointed him Quartermaster General of the United States Army in 1792. During his military career, James served in western Pennsylvania to quell the Whiskey Rebellion and in General Anthony Wayne's expedition against the Western Confederation. Anne Hemphill Herbert notes that James is credited with "saving the army with his efficient business methods and remarkable understanding of the Indian character and their various dialects."
  In 1793, James purchased land at the forks of the Ohio from the United States government, and four years later he and his partner, Major Isaac Craig, built the first glass works in America on the southern banks of the Monongahela River. James became Pittsburgh's first burgess and was a founder of the First Presbyterian Church. Materials in this series provide information on early frontier life in Pennsylvania through various personal and professional letters as well as official government reports. Also included are copies of James and Mary O'Hara's wills, which are critical in understanding the inheritance of significant property holdings that are now important to Pittsburgh's history, including Schenley Park and the Fort Pitt Block House. Accompanying these materials is H.M. Brackenridge's critique of James O'Hara's will. An obituary of James O'Hara and newspaper articles describe his role in the early development of Pittsburgh and his dealings with the Indian tribes. James O'Hara's papers have been divided into subseries that separate personal and business papers from materials describing his legacy and estate.
  - Personal and Business Papers, 1.
    Scope and Contents note
    Various personal letters written by General James O'Hara to his wife and contemporaries describe conditions at Fort Pitt and along the Miami River in the 1790s, including a comment that surrounding Indian tribes were "intent on annoying our Frontiers." A number of items relate to James O'Hara's land, including a 1785 land office record that documents property he owned near Campbell's Run, and a lease agreement for land in Robinson Township. A letter, court decision, and article of ejectment relate to a land dispute between the estates of Arthur St. Clair and James O'Hara. Transcriptions of James' diary include his opinions on immigration, and mention the glassworks that he built.
    - James O'Hara to Devereaux Smith, April 8, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - James O'Hara to Mary Carson O'Hara, October 3, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Diary (typed transcript), 1795-1804 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Official Land Office record, October 17, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report on transportation, southwest branch of the Miami River, October 23, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Receipt of Business Exchange, August 26, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Lease agreement between James O'Hara and J. Benny, March 1805 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letter written by James O'Hara to Arthur St Clair, July 27, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Judgment for James O'Hara, December 29, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Survey of Land Ownership, September 20, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Article on Ejectment from court, February 1846 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Law suit, January, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Genealogy, Estate and Legacy, 2.
    Included are the wills of both James and Mary O'Hara, along with an essay written by Henry Marie Brackenridge critiquing the will of James O'Hara. Materials related to his estate include an article describing Mary E. Schenley's law suit against James O'Hara's executors and an 1881 newspaper clipping entitled "Sheriff"s Sales". James O'Hara's obituary and a number of brief, typed excerpts from the Pittsburgh Gazette, Pittsburgh Mercury, and the Pennsylvania Archives describe General James O'Hara and some of his accomplishments in the military. In an additional published item, John Heckewelder discusses General O'Hara's influence on the interaction between Indians and settlers. The collection also contains a typed O'Hara family genealogy, a family biography, and two portraits of James O'Hara.
    - "Sheriff's Sales" clipping, March 7, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Typed excerpts from newspapers, 1786-1842 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - James O'Hara's Will, September 15, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Obituary of James O'Hara, December 21, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Extract of Mary Carson O'Hara's Will, October 10, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Mary Carson O'Hara's Will, November 15, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Essay by Henry Marie Brackenridge, August 15, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Printed anecdote, "Indian Fidelity", mentioning James O'Hara, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - List of O'Hara Family members, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - O'Hara family Biography and Portrait of James O'Hara, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Benjamin Darlington Papers, 1815-1852; II.
  Benjamin Darlington (1790-1856), one of Pittsburgh's elite businessmen and benefactors of the 1800's, was the husband of Agnes McCullough and father of William M. Darlington. Benjamin Darlington owned a thriving store and hotel, and eventually his wealth, prestige and family connections presented him with the opportunity to assist in leading the Allegheny Valley Railroad Company. Benjamin Darlington was the fourth generation of Darlingtons in the United States. Benjamin Darlington began as a carpenter's apprentice. After working in a store on Market Street, he gained enough capital to buy a hardware store with his brother, Samuel Darlington, and later owned one of Pittsburgh's only hotels. In 1833, he was elected president of the Allegheny Engine and Hose Company, and by 1837 he was one of the first officers on the Board of Trustees for Pittsburgh's Gas Works. Benjamin Darlington served as commissioner for the Allegheny Valley Railroad Company and contributed a major donation for the building of the Pittsburgh Theater.
  The series concerning Benjamin Darlington includes documents explaining his endeavors as a successful entrepreneur while Pittsburgh was growing into a major city. The receipt books contain handwritten records of various transactions made by Benjamin Darlington, explaining his relevance to the real estate business in Pittsburgh. Listed are property holdings and rent collections including one by Alexander Brackenridge, who was at the time president of the United States Bank in Pittsburgh. Accompanying this are other transactions made by Benjamin Darlington as the executor to the estate of Jane McCullough (1766-1821), his mother-in-law. In addition to the receipt books, there are various letters to and from Benjamin Darlington, including correspondence from his brother, Samuel Darlington. A number of names appear within the two receipt books, aside from those mentioned above; a brief list follows: John Wright, James Appleton, Thomas Dickson, Jane McCullough, Anderson Evans, Jacob Negley, Irvin Boyle, Isabella Miller, Mary McCullough, Sarah Simpson, Will Porter, William Whitton, John Stewart, James Wilson, James Caoper, Jane Smith, Margaret White, and others. For more documents related to this series, see Box 25, with oversize materials.
  - Samuel Darlington to Benjamin Darlington, May 23, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Henry Baldwin to Benjamin Darlington, May 20, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Jane McCullough's Will, November 25, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Agreement between Benjamin and Samuel Darlington, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Land Survey, October 19, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Financial Papers of Benjamin Darlington, 1833-1837 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Receipt, December 5, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Acknowledgement of repayment, June 1843 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Receipt Book, 1821-1852 (Box 1a, Volume 1)
  - Receipt Book, 1833-1842 (Box 1a, Volume 2)
- William M. Darlington Papers, 1837-1889; III.
  William M. Darlington (1815-1889), was born to Benjamin Darlington and Agnes McCullough in Pittsburgh. William was educated in private schools as a child and young adult, and then went on to study at Jefferson College, now known as Washington & Jefferson College, in Pennsylvania. He began his law career under the tutelage of Richard Biddle.
  William was a devout Presbyterian, a well-respected attorney, member of the Pennsylvania Bar Association for fifty years, and Vice President of the Pennsylvania Historical Society. During the last eight years of his life, he was also a trustee of his alma mater, Jefferson College, and the Western University of Pennsylvania, now the University of Pittsburgh. William amassed an extensive collection of books, manuscripts and maps related to western Pennsylvania's colonial and revolutionary history. This library was supplemented by his wife and three eldest children.
  This series is organized into three topical subseries. Subseries 1 contains materials related to William's collecting activities, including documentation of book purchases, correspondence with booksellers and fellow collectors, historical research notes, receipts, and membership certificates to historical societies. Subseries 2 contains William's personal papers, including correspondence and diaries. Subseries 3 encompasses financial and estate papers.
  - Collection Activities and Research, 1.
    Materials in this subseries document William's collecting and lending activities, the library at Guyasuta, and his personal research and writing. William collected books and manuscripts from vendors such as the Hakluyt Society, as well as individual booksellers. Correspondence with Richard S. Edes, James Veech and Joseph Albree are examples of William's contacts in the field of rare books. Also, seventeen receipts document the purchase of books from the law offices of Baldwin & Ford, J. Munsel, and Burns & Son, among others. A bound volume of book orders, demonstrates William's meticulous documentation of the books he ordered between November 30, 1847 and January 14, 1867, including the Audubon volumes. William's correspondence with A. Eaton, John Newton, J.M. Read, J. R. Lambdin, and W.C. Reichel all highlight his role as a consultant for other researchers, to whom he sometimes lent or sold books.
    The great strength of this subseries is the documentation of volumes in the library at Guyasuta. The Classification of Books consists of three successive versions of a list of books in the library at Guyasuta. Mary used these three volumes to alphabetically catalog the books in the Darlington family library according to topic, including history, travels, horticulture and natural history, and poetry, drama and tales; sections also list magazines, newspapers, and maps. In addition to these larger volumes, this subseries includes a partial catalog and a partial inventory of books at Guyasuta; these smaller lists most likely repeat titles already listed in the Classification of Books. Additionally, design diagrams for library bookcases shed light on the original physical arrangement of the Guyasuta library.
    William was deeply interested in historical research, as was his professional mentor, Richard Biddle, and this subseries contains bound volumes of William's notes and writings about various topics. His Commonplace Book and Research Notes discuss a variety of topics, including: the Ohio Company; Forts Pitt, Duquesne, Shippen and Kittanning; Guyasuta; the Allegheny River and the city of Pittsburgh; Old Westmoreland and Indiana Counties; the Montour family; the Shawnee (Shananese) and Seneca Indians; George Croghan and Henry Alexander; and shipbuilding and theater. The Historical Biographical Notes include William's thoughts on such diverse topics as the Californian coal mountains, British nobility, the Darlington family crest, American Indian rituals, and the papers of British officer Henry Bouquet (1719-1765). This subseries contains transcriptions of the Bouquet Papers, which William commissioned from the British Museum. The transcribed letters document communication between Colonel Bouquet and other British officers during the French and Indian War from locations throughout Pennsylvania, his military campaign to drive the French out of Fort Duquesne, and the battle with Indians at Bushy Run. William was profoundly interested in the Ohio Company, and collected many papers relating to this eighteenth century land-development and trading consortium, including copies of the journals of Christopher Gist, who was hired by the company to negotiate terms with the Indians. William published Christopher Gist's Journals posthumously in 1893, possibly using transcriptions in this subseries. The drafts of his publication are located in the collection number dar192514.